A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Population Program, Office Files of Stuart Burden FA598
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Population Program, Office Files of Stuart Burden
1984-1989
Rockefeller Archive Center
Burden, Stuart
Ford Foundation
FA598
0.76 Cubic Feet 2 document boxes
Stuart Burden served as a Program Associate in both the Population and the Human Rights and Governance programs from 1986 to 1989. During this time he guided the Foundation's activities related to the AIDS epidemic of the 1980s. He also handled grant requests concerning reproductive health issues, family planning programs and women's health initiatives. The Office Files of Stuart Burden span from 1986 to 1989 and document the work of Mr. Burden and his colleagues in the Population and the Human Rights and Governance programs. The collection is organized into three series: AIDS Files, General Health Files, and Trustees' Trip Files. The bulk of the collection consists of grant proposals, grant-related correspondence, and reviews of grant-funded projects concerning AIDS awareness and prevention, as well as additional health related issues. The collection also includes materials from conferences, symposia and workshops that Mr. Burden attended as a representative of the Ford Foundation. The minutes and materials document the Foundation's interest and involvement in the field of health sciences. Mr. Burden's files also contain correspondence, surveys, trustees' biographies and press releases about the 1987 trustees' trip to Kentucky and Mississippi to review grant projects and determine their success.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Biographical / Historical
Stuart Burden served as a Program Associate in the Population and the Human Rights and Governance programs from 1986 to 1989. He graduated from Stanford University in 1984 with a Bachelor of Arts in Human Biology and later received a Master's of Health Sciences from Johns Hopkins University. He worked with a variety of health initiatives, focusing much of his efforts on the Foundation's interest in the AIDS epidemic of the 1980s. At a time when Foundation funding for research on specific diseases was relatively uncommon, he helped secure grants for several AIDS initiatives. In addition to his work with AIDS research and outreach, Mr. Burden also handled grant requests dealing with reproductive health issues, family planning programs and women's health initiatives.
Following his departure from the Ford Foundation, Mr. Burden worked for the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation where he served as a senior program officer and chairman of their Africa Task Group. After 11 years at MacArthur, he moved to Levi Strauss and Co. and the Levi Strauss Foundation. There he served in the Community Affairs Department as Director for the Americas and Europe. In addition, he managed the company's HIV/AIDS grant-making initiatives. He has served on the Board of Directors of the National Centers on Sexuality at San Francisco State University and the International Women's Health Coalition, and on the Presidential Advisory Council on HIV/AIDS under presidents Clinton and Bush. Mr. Burden currently works as a senior consultant for the Monitor Institute.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation created a Population program in 1963 to better support research and more efficiently handle grant proposals pertaining to the health of communities in the United States and abroad. Three years later, in 1966, the program became a sub-division of the International Division and remained so until 1981 when it once again became an independent program. Following a reorganization of the Foundation in 1992, the newly formed Reproductive Health and Population program absorbed the existing Population program. The ASSETS program (Asset Building and Community Development Program) was introduced in 1997 and included a subdivision focused on Human Development and Reproductive Health. Though the Human Development and Reproductive Health program was canceled in 2002, in 2009 the Education, Creativity and Free Expression program restored the Foundation's work in population health through a subdivision focused on Sexuality and Reproductive Health and Rights.
Designed to focus on similar issues as the Population program, the Human Rights and Governance (HRG) program was created in 1981 as a subdivision of the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP). Following a Foundation restructuring in 1989, the HRG program was separated from USIAP and divided into the Rights and Social Justice and the Governance and Public Policy programs. These two programs later merged in a subsequent 1997 corporate restructuring which created the Peace and Social Justice program. Following another restructuring in 2009, the Peace and Social Justice program became the Democracy, Rights and Justice program, and focused on three key issues: Democratic and Accountable Government, Human Rights, and Social Justice Philanthropy.
Separated Materials
There are no separated materials.
Arrangement
Records are arranged into 3 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. AIDS Files, 1987-1989
Series II. General Health Files, 1986-1989
Series III. Trustees Trip, 1984-1987, bulk 1986-1987
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Stuart Burden span from 1984 to 1989 and document his work for both the Population and the Human Rights and Governance programs. The collection is organized into three series: AIDS Files, General Health Files, and Trustees' Trip Files. The bulk of the collection dates from 1986-1989 and consists of grant proposals and documentation of grant-funded projects, including initiatives in AIDS awareness and prevention, women's health and reproductive rights, family planning, and improved hygiene.
The grant proposals and related correspondence between applicants and Ford employees describe studies being implemented and conducted at a time when AIDS research was still in its nascent stage. The AIDS-related proposals found within the collection provide details of the Foundation's earliest responses to the epidemic and what was then known of the disease.
The collection also contains materials from conferences, symposia and workshops Mr. Burden attended as a representative of the Ford Foundation. The minutes and materials from these events provide an overview of the work being done in the health sciences field during the late 1980s and document the Foundation's interest and involvement. Mr. Burden's files also detail the 1987 trustees' trip to Kentucky and Mississippi during which trustees met with grant recipients to gauge the work accomplished through Foundation support.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- AIDS Files, 1987-1989; I
  Arrangement
  The grant-related files are arranged in alphabetical order by the name of the requesting agency.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of grant proposals, funding requests, and correspondence related to AIDS research. There is also a file of charts concerning the Foundation's projected grant-making activity for AIDS-related requests. Though much of the correspondence regarding grant proposals was addressed directly to Shepard Forman, Director of the Human Rights and Governance program, Mr. Burden appears to have shared responsibility for handling the incoming mail. Responses by Mr. Forman and Mr. Burden to grant-related inquiries reveal the Foundation's burgeoning interest in AIDS research and contain information regarding the team of consultants hired by the Foundation to determine how best to initiate programs to respond to the epidemic. This series also includes one folder of materials from "AIDS and Reproductive Health," a workshop organized by Harvard University's School of Public Health. Mr. Burden participated in the workshop as a Ford Foundation representative.
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- Adolescent Treatment and Education Alliance, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- Association of the Bar of the City of New York, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- Human Interaction Research Institute, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- World Future Society, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Grant Spending Projections, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Workshops, Symposia -- Woods Hole Workshop, "AIDS and Reproductive Health" (Harvard University School of Public Health), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- General Health Files, 1986-1989; II
  Arranged alphabetically by the name of the requesting agency or individual.
  The General Health Files consist of grant proposals, funding requests, correspondence and grantee reports concerning non-AIDS related health issues. Most of the grant-requests found within this series received Foundation support and focus on women's health, family planning, nutrition and hygiene in underdeveloped countries and among at-risk populations. The funded projects include a television series designed to address public health issues proposed by the Center for Development and Communication in Cairo, Egypt; a compendium of family planning and child survival data of one hundred developing countries compiled by the Center for Population and Family Health at Columbia University; and the development of maternal morbidity studies in India, Bangladesh and Egypt. This series also contains materials pertaining to a panel discussion hosted by the International Women's Health Coalition and a Women for Women's Health meeting that Mr. Burden attended on behalf of the Ford Foundation.
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- Boston Women's Health Book Collective, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- Center for Development Communication (Cairo), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- Center for Population and Family Health, Including Report from Previous Ford Funding, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- Family Health International, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, Centre for Population Studies, and Measurement of Maternal Health Luncheon Materials, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- Population Resource Center/Population Reference Bureau, "America in the 21st Century" Project, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- Program for Appropriate Technology in Health (PATH), Including Annual Report (folder 1 of 2), 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Grant Proposals and Funding Requests -- Program for Appropriate Technology in Health (PATH), Including Annual Report (folder 2 of 2), 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Workshops, Symposia -- International Women's Health Coalition, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Workshops, Symposia -- Women for Women's Health, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Trustees Trip, 1984-1987, bulk 1986-1987; 1986-1987; III
  Three folders of documents, arranged in chronological order, pertain to the October 1987 trustees' trip to Kentucky and Mississippi. Ford Foundation trustees met with Foundation grantees in both states to learn firsthand about their activities and judge their success. The correspondence for the trip suggests that Mr. Burden handled much of the planning, including coordinating with the grantees prior to the site visits. A press release from the 1984 Board of Trustees' trip to Arizona and New Mexico is also included within the series.
  - Correspondence Re: Trip Planning, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Trustees' Biographies and Trip Scheduling Surveys, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Press Releases and Press Reports Re: Board Trips, 1984, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)